<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-16T23:54:05-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Instrumental Convergence</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Twich Plays Battle Bots</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/hackathon/2019/02/16/mhacks-battlebots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Twich Plays Battle Bots" /><published>2019-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/hackathon/2019/02/16/mhacks-battlebots</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/hackathon/2019/02/16/mhacks-battlebots.html">&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the surprisingly interesting social experiment known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twitch_Plays_Pok%C3%A9mon&quot;&gt;Twitch Plays Pokemon&lt;/a&gt;, we made Twitch chat-controlled cars that could play two games. Throw in some computer vision, Arduino, etc. and you get this monstrosity. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cdsupina/MHacks2016&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/GitHub-Mark-32px.png&quot; alt=&quot;Github repo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mhacks1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our Arduino setup at MHacks&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mhacks2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full view of the battle bots&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mhacks3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Close up of the battle bots&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="hackathon" /><summary type="html">Inspired by the surprisingly interesting social experiment known as Twitch Plays Pokemon, we made Twitch chat-controlled cars that could play two games. Throw in some computer vision, Arduino, etc. and you get this monstrosity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Assignment Problem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/assignment-problem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Assignment Problem" /><published>2019-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/assignment-problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/assignment-problem.html">&lt;p&gt;Consider placing $n$ individuals in $n$ jobs given ratings for each. This gives a matrix $(a_{ij})$ of the rating of individual $i$ at job $j$. Find an efficient method of assigning one person to each job to maximize the total rating. Scanning all $n!$ possibilities is a bad option because even placing only 50 individuals would require $3 \cdot 10^{64}$ cases to check. The algorithm described here runs in $O(n^3)$ which corresponds to $\approx 10^5$ for 50 individuals. Quite an improvement! I first studied this problem as an extremely simple case of a problem in geometric analysis called Monge-Kantorovich Mass Transfer. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/848c/717ba51e48afef714dfef4bd6ab1cc050dab.pdf&quot;&gt;A paper&lt;/a&gt; by the great topologist James Munkres outlines a solution, from which I adapted this &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/munkres_assignment_algo.py&quot;&gt;Python implementation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">Consider placing $n$ individuals in $n$ jobs given ratings for each. This gives a matrix $(a_{ij})$ of the rating of individual $i$ at job $j$. Find an efficient method of assigning one person to each job to maximize the total rating. Scanning all $n!$ possibilities is a bad option because even placing only 50 individuals would require $3 \cdot 10^{64}$ cases to check. The algorithm described here runs in $O(n^3)$ which corresponds to $\approx 10^5$ for 50 individuals. Quite an improvement! I first studied this problem as an extremely simple case of a problem in geometric analysis called Monge-Kantorovich Mass Transfer. A paper by the great topologist James Munkres outlines a solution, from which I adapted this Python implementation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Transportation Problem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/transportation_problem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Transportation Problem" /><published>2019-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/transportation_problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/transportation_problem.html">&lt;p&gt;Consider a market in which there are $m$ sellers of a good/service and $n$ buyers, each of whom are selling/buying a specific amount. Assume further that there is a cost matrix $(c_{ij})$ that represents the unit cost of seller $i$ doing business with buyer $j$. Give an efficient method of clearing the market at a minimal total cost. This is a generalization of the assignment problem and has a fairly similar solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/848c/717ba51e48afef714dfef4bd6ab1cc050dab.pdf&quot;&gt;A paper&lt;/a&gt; by the great topologist James Munkres outlines a solution.
Here are some examples:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">Consider a market in which there are $m$ sellers of a good/service and $n$ buyers, each of whom are selling/buying a specific amount. Assume further that there is a cost matrix $(c_{ij})$ that represents the unit cost of seller $i$ doing business with buyer $j$. Give an efficient method of clearing the market at a minimal total cost. This is a generalization of the assignment problem and has a fairly similar solution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Case Against Constant Economic Growth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/2019/01/07/gdp_nonconstant_growth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Case Against Constant Economic Growth" /><published>2019-01-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/2019/01/07/gdp_nonconstant_growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/2019/01/07/gdp_nonconstant_growth.html">&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a consensus among politicians, economists, and political scientists that a constant rate of economic growth is necessary to satisfy the (American) population and ensure political stability. “It’s the economy, stupid,” as President Clinton espoused. During every presidential election, candidates frequently set goals to expand the GDP by x percent. Markets go in a frenzy when China’s GDP growth rate falls from 12% in the early 2000s to a &lt;em&gt;measly&lt;/em&gt; 6.5% today. This sentiment ignores the history of economic growth, its fundamental purpose, and creates a society that is dependent on materialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need a bit of a mathematical background. A constant rate of growth of GDP (or any numerical quantity, for that matter) is one way of defining &lt;strong&gt;exponential growth&lt;/strong&gt;. Any student who takes an introductory course in differential equation will invariably see an equation resembling the following: $\frac{dy}{dt} = ky$. For our purposes, we consider the case where $k &amp;gt; 0$. This means that the rate of change in $y$ or the GDP will grow as the GDP itself grows. In other words, the GDP accelerates. The only solutions to this equation are of the form $y = Ce^{kt}$ where $C$ depends on an initial condition for $y$. That this solves the differential equation is clear from plugging it in. Uniqueness follows from the Contraction Mapping Theorem. This leads to the fact that &lt;strong&gt;constant growth in GDP means that the GDP grows exponentially&lt;/strong&gt;. This should raise a red flag because exponential growth is always unsustainable, usually undesirable, and sometimes catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following graph of the global GDP since 0 AD. &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gdp.svg&quot; alt=&quot;A &amp;quot;hockey stick&amp;quot; graph of global GDP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is quite remarkable. Pause here for atleast 30 minutes to take that in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a fact to consider when looking at this image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The annual rate of growth in the Western world from AD 1 to AD 1820 was a mere 0.06 percent per year, or 6 percent per century” (Gordon 3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how flat this curve is for about 1800 years. The effects of the American and European industrializations, economic miracles of the BRICS (namely China), and rapid diversification of labor facilitated an explosion of industrial, creative, and technological output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who is surprised by the above graph, however, does not know the first thing about economic growth. Thus we conclude: the transformations of the past 200 years are abnormal in the context of human history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I refuse to make pull a Francis Fukuyama with the trajectory of the human story. The next 50 to 100 years are going to be crucial in securing the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;![]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">There seems to be a consensus among politicians, economists, and political scientists that a constant rate of economic growth is necessary to satisfy the (American) population and ensure political stability. “It’s the economy, stupid,” as President Clinton espoused. During every presidential election, candidates frequently set goals to expand the GDP by x percent. Markets go in a frenzy when China’s GDP growth rate falls from 12% in the early 2000s to a measly 6.5% today. This sentiment ignores the history of economic growth, its fundamental purpose, and creates a society that is dependent on materialism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Anthology of the American Golden Age</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2019/01/05/gordon-growth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anthology of the American Golden Age" /><published>2019-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2019/01/05/gordon-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2019/01/05/gordon-growth.html">&lt;p&gt;Most high school U.S. history courses focus on what I consider to be the most dull aspects of the subject. While an understanding of major political forces, wars, and social movements is invaluable in understanding the American story, focusing on these aspects can send the message that history is driven by individuals, rather than institutions that while certainly constructed by individuals, operate as forms of distributed intelligence. An equally valid lens through which one can (and should) understand American history is as a march of of science and technology that shape the lives of individuals via markets. Focusing on a period of American history that is approachable and relavent illustrates this utility of this perspective. This book synthesizes Professor Gordon’s research throughout much of his career, starting from his time in graduate school and the thoroughness sings off of the pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the book argues the following: The period between 1870–1970 was the golden age of American growth and featured an unprecedented improvement in the standard of living for the vast majority of Americans. While the 21st century will certainly contain its fair share of “general purpose” technologies that will be transformative in their own ways, the growth and accompanied imporvements in the standard of living will not match those of the previous century. To claim that the following century will be as revolutionary as the previous, one must argue that new technologies (i.e. AI, renewable energy, self driving cars, quantum computing, etc.) will be as imporotant in the every day lives of Americans as was the advent of running water, refridgeration, and electricity. Indeed this is a highly nontrivial argumentative burden. Most of the book focuses on explaining the effect of growth on everyday life. This includes changes in diet, work life, entertainment, communication, transportation, and health. I enjoy this approach to American history because it puts you in the shoes of individuals and offers a much more vivid understanding of the relavent time period than political and military history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claim that 1870–1970 was the golden age of growth is a relatively straightforward proposition, but has certain complications. Namely, the U.S. government only started recording GDP in the 1930’s and the metric was changed many times in the following decades to better reflect total productivity in the economy. TODO: Include a brief discussion of some of the interesting sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I claim that GDP has become much less tied to the standard of living than it was in the early 1900s and that improvements in standard of living in the developed world will be almost entirely decoupled from GDP growth in the 21st century, but that is a more subtle argument for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For argument’s sake, I will grant his premise that GDP gr&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;GDP $\neq$ Standard of Living&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A central premise of the book undermines its thesis. In particular, GDP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-takeaways&quot;&gt;Main Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is hard to overstate the magnitude of the anomalous growth in the 1870-1970 period. Based on estimates by Angus Maddison,
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The annual rate of growth in the Western world from AD 1 to AD 1820 was a mere 0.06 percent per year, or 6 percent per century” (Gordon 3).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that does not blow your mind, then you did not read that correctly. It would take about 1000 years for annual production to double, which means that an individual living in almost any time in human history (a time period encompassing ~98% of the human age) could reasonably expect her standard of living to be approximately equal to that of her (great great great) grandparents and her (great great great) grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gordon, Robert J. The Rise and Fall of American Growth: the U.S. Standard of Living since the Civil War. Princeton University Press, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Gordon</name></author><category term="bookreview" /><summary type="html">Most high school U.S. history courses focus on what I consider to be the most dull aspects of the subject. While an understanding of major political forces, wars, and social movements is invaluable in understanding the American story, focusing on these aspects can send the message that history is driven by individuals, rather than institutions that while certainly constructed by individuals, operate as forms of distributed intelligence. An equally valid lens through which one can (and should) understand American history is as a march of of science and technology that shape the lives of individuals via markets. Focusing on a period of American history that is approachable and relavent illustrates this utility of this perspective. This book synthesizes Professor Gordon’s research throughout much of his career, starting from his time in graduate school and the thoroughness sings off of the pages.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gazing into the Abyss</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/12/21/browning-ordinary-men.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gazing into the Abyss" /><published>2018-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/12/21/browning-ordinary-men</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/12/21/browning-ordinary-men.html">&lt;p&gt;I first heard of this book, strangely enough, through an online lecture by Jordan Peterson. During the summer of 2018, I was asking myself questions about the role of political leaders and the extent to which they do/should reflect the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The idea that leaders ought to reflect the desires of their constituents is almost axiomatic to most Americans. To what extent does this idea remain valid if a leader disagrees with his/her constituents? To what extent should leaders shape the psyche of the nation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting aside the main architects of atrocities, how does a large subset of the population bring itself to carry out the orders of madmen? It seems that there would need to be problems worth identifying at every level of society.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can we prevent such devolution at the levels of individuals, communities, nations, and global community?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe civilizations fall when an uncomfortably large number of individuals becomes agents of its destruction. It seems plausible that guarding against the worst tendencies of humanity will always be a duty of the citizenry. Those tendencies certainly include hatred, envy, and jealosy, but they also include an excessive desire to impress others, a false sense of honor or pride, and an unquestioned submission to authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, this book is not an attempt to psychoanalyze one of maybe 100-1000 commited idealogues with influence. That is the job of many college seniors who decide to read &lt;em&gt;Mein Kampf&lt;/em&gt; while high. Rather, &lt;em&gt;Ordinary Men&lt;/em&gt; tries to shed light on why millions others enabled the vision of a minority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ordinary Men&lt;/em&gt; follows a single battalion of about 500 men during the occupation of Poland. They were part of the Order Police, which is separate from the main army. They were tasked, among other things, with making parts of Poland &lt;em&gt;judenfrei&lt;/em&gt;. In total, these men killed at least 83,000 jews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the the book uses the testimonies of about 125 men during interrogations conducted in the 1960’s. Care must be taken when reading these because memories fade, people suppress certain thoughts, and soldiers may care to exculpate themselves and comrades. Browning also uses soldiers’ personal correspondances sent during the war, along with ample Nazi government records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My takeaway of the book is as follows: Idealogical exremism tautologically represents a small fringe and winning over hearts and minds by the tens of millions is immensely difficult. Those who wish  included 
One minor critique of the book is that there are so many names and ranks to keep track of that many individuals blur together. New soldiers are introduced even at the end of the book. This is complicated by the fact that some people enter and leave the battalion. I recommend keeping track of the consequential people in a notebook and not getting bogged down in the minutia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book mostly tracks the progression from the formation of the battalion,&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christopher Browning</name></author><category term="bookreview" /><summary type="html">I first heard of this book, strangely enough, through an online lecture by Jordan Peterson. During the summer of 2018, I was asking myself questions about the role of political leaders and the extent to which they do/should reflect the population. The idea that leaders ought to reflect the desires of their constituents is almost axiomatic to most Americans. To what extent does this idea remain valid if a leader disagrees with his/her constituents? To what extent should leaders shape the psyche of the nation? Setting aside the main architects of atrocities, how does a large subset of the population bring itself to carry out the orders of madmen? It seems that there would need to be problems worth identifying at every level of society. How can we prevent such devolution at the levels of individuals, communities, nations, and global community?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mathematics for Everyday Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/08/20/ellenberg-math.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mathematics for Everyday Life" /><published>2018-08-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/08/20/ellenberg-math</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/08/20/ellenberg-math.html">&lt;p&gt;Why should I study math? When will I ever use it? What lessons can the work of mathematicians across the  millenia have for every person in the 21st century? These are the questions that Professor Ellenberg tackles in his phenomenal book. I asked the first two questions rather frequently as a child. I even asked those during my undergraduate and graduate studies! It is natural to ask such questions given that much of modern mathematics seemingly bears little on the natural world. A valid critique of the “unreasonable effectiveness” of mathematics mimics that of “Higher Order Truths About Chmess” by Daniel Dennett. Here are some answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract problems are excellent cross training. Solving such problems sharpens one’s thinking and prepares the mathematical community for more applied problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some problems are much easier to solve at a higher level of analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rather than solve individual problems, it is much more efficent to solve a &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt; of problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solving hard problems, regardless of immediate utility, is fun! There are few feelings that can match that of an epiphany after hours, days, or even years of struggle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mathematician, certain parts of this book seemed obvious when I first read them. For example, of course most important phenomena do not depend linearly on their determinants. Simple regression analyses have important limitations. It needs very little justification that “mathematical expectation” does not refer to the result that one should expect to occur in an average case. These truisms became apparent to me through courses in econometrics, probability, and common sense. However, it is always useful to remember that none of these statements are actually trivial. Their justifications each took a tremendous amount of effort by mathematicians (and those in related fields) to understand deeply. This book tells many of those stories. The intelligencia of yestyear was wrong about many things. But the nature of their errors are educational and sometimes teach more than refined arguments and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During many of my mathematics classes in high school, undergraduate school, and even graduate school, I solved problems and nurtured ways of thinking as if the ideas existed in some alternate reality analagous to Paul Erdos’ conceptualization of “God’s book.” Understanding the stories of these ideas helps to humanize them and contextualize them in everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Criticism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second minor critique proceeds as follows. The book seems poorly titled. A better subtitle may be something of the sort &lt;em&gt;The Power of &lt;strong&gt;Statistical&lt;/strong&gt; Thinking&lt;/em&gt; given that most of the book focuses on lessons of probability and statistics. Professor Ellenberg addresses this by noting that statistics grew out of mathematics and that ideas of probability manifest themselves in many branches of math. Nonetheles,&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jordan Ellenberg</name></author><category term="bookreview" /><summary type="html">Why should I study math? When will I ever use it? What lessons can the work of mathematicians across the millenia have for every person in the 21st century? These are the questions that Professor Ellenberg tackles in his phenomenal book. I asked the first two questions rather frequently as a child. I even asked those during my undergraduate and graduate studies! It is natural to ask such questions given that much of modern mathematics seemingly bears little on the natural world. A valid critique of the “unreasonable effectiveness” of mathematics mimics that of “Higher Order Truths About Chmess” by Daniel Dennett. Here are some answers.</summary></entry></feed>