<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-13T12:02:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Instrumental Convergence</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Computing The Convex Hull in $\mathbb{R}^2$</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/03/06/convex_hull_algos.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computing The Convex Hull in $\mathbb{R}^2$" /><published>2019-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/code/2019/03/06/convex_hull_algos</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/03/06/convex_hull_algos.html">&lt;p&gt;There are many classical algorithms to compute the convex hull of a finite point set in the plane, but I chose to implement three. Jarvis Matching involves iteratively adding points to the hull as to mimimize a turning angle. It runs in $O(nh)$ where $h$ is the number of points in the hull. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.ucsd.edu/~ronspubs/72_10_convex_hull.pdf&quot;&gt;Graham scan&lt;/a&gt; iterates through groupings of three points naturally induced by modified polar coordinates, allowing it to reduce to two simple cases. Ronald Graham’s algorithm runs in $O(n \log(n))$. I created these &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/jarvismatch.py&quot;&gt;Python implementations&lt;/a&gt; from the original papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;convexhull_pics&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/convexhull_7pts_scaled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The outline of the convex hull of seven planar points.&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;The outline of the convex hull of seven planar points.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/convexhull_250kpts_scaled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Convex hull of 250,000 points.&quot; /&gt; 
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Convex hull of 250,000 points.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">There are many classical algorithms to compute the convex hull of a finite point set in the plane, but I chose to implement three. Jarvis Matching involves iteratively adding points to the hull as to mimimize a turning angle. It runs in $O(nh)$ where $h$ is the number of points in the hull. The Graham scan iterates through groupings of three points naturally induced by modified polar coordinates, allowing it to reduce to two simple cases. Ronald Graham’s algorithm runs in $O(n \log(n))$. I created these Python implementations from the original papers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Counterfactuals in Economic History</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/paper/2019/02/28/econ_counterfactuals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counterfactuals in Economic History" /><published>2019-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/paper/2019/02/28/econ_counterfactuals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/paper/2019/02/28/econ_counterfactuals.html">&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed &lt;img src=&quot;https://vita.mcafee.cc/PDF/VoyageofColumbus.pdf&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot; /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#mcafee_counterfactual&quot;&gt;(McAfee, 1983)&lt;/a&gt; paper by Preston McAfee on so many levels. McAfee responds to an argument by the late economic historian Robert Fogel that the railroads were not as critical to the development of the U.S. as historians have claimed &lt;a href=&quot;#fogel_railroad&quot;&gt;(Fogel, 1962)&lt;/a&gt;. In arguing this, Fogel estimated things such as the the value of time lost in water transportation, cargo loss, and “social savings” of the railroads (whatever that means). Ultimately, Fogel estimates that the “social saving” attributable to the railroads is approximately 1% of national income. Basically, the type of counterfactual analysis of Fogel allows for so much subjectivity as to …. Also if one is interested on the effects of trains/infrastructure spending on some battery of economic indicators, there are FAR better sources at the disposal of any economist, though I am not sure that was the case in the 1960’s when&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;PROOF: For a proof, send $8.99 to Proof, Box 666, London, Canada (Canadians add $6.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to know if this is true in general. That is, is it the case that, for all $\epsilon &amp;gt; 0$, a $\delta &amp;gt; 0$ exists so that, if history is perturbed by less than $\delta$, then America is perturbed by less than $\epsilon$? In this case, America would be continuous, and hence integrable. One might then wonder if the United States converges in probability to what it will be, as time diverges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Critics of counterfactuals have charged that, given the inability to forecast the U.S. economy even months in advance, and the dearth of all but the most coarse data on historical events, it is absurd to expect to reconstruct how th economy would have been if it were different. There are three avenues of response to this…First, the inability to forecast the modern economy is irrelevent, for the economy was simpler in the old days. Second, if the data are coarse, one can use the coarse topology to analyze them. Thus, no theoretical impediments exist to applying counterfactuals, although it is interesting to suppose they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fogel’s defense, he is rather cautious about the limitations of his work, but that is drowned out by the rest of the 40 pages of dubious guess work. About 10 years after McAfee published his response, Fogel won the Nobel Prize in Economics “for having renewed research in economic history by applying economic theory and quantitative methods in order to explain economic and institutional change.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize my takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="paper" /><summary type="html">I enjoyed (McAfee, 1983) paper by Preston McAfee on so many levels. McAfee responds to an argument by the late economic historian Robert Fogel that the railroads were not as critical to the development of the U.S. as historians have claimed (Fogel, 1962). In arguing this, Fogel estimated things such as the the value of time lost in water transportation, cargo loss, and “social savings” of the railroads (whatever that means). Ultimately, Fogel estimates that the “social saving” attributable to the railroads is approximately 1% of national income. Basically, the type of counterfactual analysis of Fogel allows for so much subjectivity as to …. Also if one is interested on the effects of trains/infrastructure spending on some battery of economic indicators, there are FAR better sources at the disposal of any economist, though I am not sure that was the case in the 1960’s when</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Twich Plays Battle Bots</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/hackathon/2019/02/16/mhacks-battlebots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Twich Plays Battle Bots" /><published>2019-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/hackathon/2019/02/16/mhacks-battlebots</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/hackathon/2019/02/16/mhacks-battlebots.html">&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the surprisingly interesting social experiment known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twitch_Plays_Pok%C3%A9mon&quot;&gt;Twitch Plays Pokemon&lt;/a&gt;, we made Twitch chat-controlled cars that could play two games. Throw in some computer vision, Arduino, etc. and you get this monstrosity. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cdsupina/MHacks2016&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. My hackathon projects are on &lt;a href=&quot;https://devpost.com/pazhyanurv?ref_content=user-portfolio&amp;amp;ref_feature=portfolio&amp;amp;ref_medium=global-nav&quot;&gt;Devpost&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mhacks_pics&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;three_adjacent_pics&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mhacks1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our Arduino setup at MHacks&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;three_adjacent_pics&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mhacks2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full view of the battle bots&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;three_adjacent_pics&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/mhacks3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Close up of the battle bots&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="hackathon" /><summary type="html">Inspired by the surprisingly interesting social experiment known as Twitch Plays Pokemon, we made Twitch chat-controlled cars that could play two games. Throw in some computer vision, Arduino, etc. and you get this monstrosity. Github repo. My hackathon projects are on Devpost.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The (Linear Sum) Assignment Problem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/assignment-problem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The (Linear Sum) Assignment Problem" /><published>2019-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/assignment-problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/code/2019/02/15/assignment-problem.html">&lt;p&gt;Consider the problem of placing $n$ individuals into $n$ jobs given a matrix $(a_{ij})$ of the rating of individual $i$ at job $j$. The problem is to find an efficient construction of the optimal assignment. In other words, for any square matrix, pick a sum-maximizing(or minimizing) set of elements that do no share a row or column. In the case where the cost marix is binary, this algorithm also solves the problem of picking a maximal set of nonattacking rooks given such an arrangement on a chess board. I created a &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/munkres_assignment_algo.py&quot;&gt;Python implementation&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;em&gt;Hungarian Algorithm&lt;/em&gt; or the &lt;em&gt;Kuhn-Munkres Algorthm&lt;/em&gt; from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/848c/717ba51e48afef714dfef4bd6ab1cc050dab.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; by James Munkres. These types of problems were the subject of the 1975 Nobel Prize in Economics won by Leonid Kantorovich and Tjalling Koopmans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples: &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/assignment_small.txt&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/assignment_mid.txt&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/assignment_large.txt&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solutions: &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/assignment_small_solution.txt&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/assignment_mid_solution.txt&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/assignment_large_solution.txt&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">Consider the problem of placing $n$ individuals into $n$ jobs given a matrix $(a_{ij})$ of the rating of individual $i$ at job $j$. The problem is to find an efficient construction of the optimal assignment. In other words, for any square matrix, pick a sum-maximizing(or minimizing) set of elements that do no share a row or column. In the case where the cost marix is binary, this algorithm also solves the problem of picking a maximal set of nonattacking rooks given such an arrangement on a chess board. I created a Python implementation of the Hungarian Algorithm or the Kuhn-Munkres Algorthm from a paper by James Munkres. These types of problems were the subject of the 1975 Nobel Prize in Economics won by Leonid Kantorovich and Tjalling Koopmans.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Case Against Constant Economic Growth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essay/2019/01/07/gdp_nonconstant_growth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Case Against Constant Economic Growth" /><published>2019-01-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essay/2019/01/07/gdp_nonconstant_growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essay/2019/01/07/gdp_nonconstant_growth.html">&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a consensus among politicians, economists, and political scientists that a constant rate of economic growth is necessary to satisfy the (American) population and ensure political stability. “It’s the economy, stupid,” as President Clinton espoused. During every presidential election, candidates frequently set goals to expand the GDP by x percent. Markets go in a frenzy when China’s GDP growth rate falls from 12% in the early 2000s to a &lt;em&gt;measly&lt;/em&gt; 6.5% today. This sentiment ignores the history of economic growth, its fundamental purpose, and creates a society that is dependent on materialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need a bit of a mathematical background. A constant rate of growth of GDP (or any numerical quantity, for that matter) is one way of defining &lt;strong&gt;exponential growth&lt;/strong&gt;. Any student who takes an introductory course in differential equation will invariably see an equation resembling the following: $\frac{dy}{dt} = ky$. For our purposes, we consider the case where $k &amp;gt; 0$. This means that the rate of change in $y$ or the GDP will grow as the GDP itself grows. In other words, the GDP accelerates. The only solutions to this equation are of the form $y = Ce^{kt}$ where $C$ depends on an initial condition for $y$. That this solves the differential equation is clear from plugging it in. Uniqueness follows from the Contraction Mapping Theorem. This leads to the fact that &lt;strong&gt;constant growth in GDP means that the GDP grows exponentially&lt;/strong&gt;. This should raise a red flag because exponential growth is always unsustainable, usually undesirable, and sometimes catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following graph of the global GDP since 0 AD&amp;lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&lt;span id=&quot;owideconomicgrowth&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant: small-caps&quot;&gt;Roser&lt;/span&gt;, M. (2019) Economic Growth. &lt;i&gt;Our World in Data&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gordon2016growth&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant: small-caps&quot;&gt;Gordon&lt;/span&gt;, R.J. (2016) &lt;i&gt;k^2 The Rise and Fall of American Growth: The U.S. Standard of Living since the Civil War&lt;/i&gt;. , The Princeton Economic History of the Western World. Princeton University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;fogel_railroad&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant: small-caps&quot;&gt;Fogel&lt;/span&gt;, R.W. (1962) A Quantitative Approach to the Study of Railroads in American Economic Growth: A Report of Some Preliminary Findings. &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Economic History&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;b&gt;22&lt;/b&gt;, 163–197.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mcafee_counterfactual&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant: small-caps&quot;&gt;McAfee&lt;/span&gt;, R. (1983) American Economic Growth and the Voyage of Columbus. &lt;i&gt;American Economic Review&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;b&gt;73&lt;/b&gt;, 735–740.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;. &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/gdp.svg&quot; alt=&quot;A &amp;quot;hockey stick&amp;quot; graph of global GDP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is quite remarkable. Pause here for atleast 30 minutes to take that in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a fact to consider when looking at this image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The annual rate of growth in the Western world from AD 1 to AD 1820 was a mere 0.06 percent per year, or 6 percent per century” &lt;a href=&quot;#gordon2016growth&quot;&gt;(Gordon, 2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essay" /><summary type="html">There seems to be a consensus among politicians, economists, and political scientists that a constant rate of economic growth is necessary to satisfy the (American) population and ensure political stability. “It’s the economy, stupid,” as President Clinton espoused. During every presidential election, candidates frequently set goals to expand the GDP by x percent. Markets go in a frenzy when China’s GDP growth rate falls from 12% in the early 2000s to a measly 6.5% today. This sentiment ignores the history of economic growth, its fundamental purpose, and creates a society that is dependent on materialism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Anthology of the American Golden Age</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2019/01/05/gordon-growth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anthology of the American Golden Age" /><published>2019-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2019/01/05/gordon-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2019/01/05/gordon-growth.html">&lt;p&gt;Most high school U.S. history courses focus on what I consider to be the dullest aspects of the subject. While an understanding of major political forces, wars, and social movements is invaluable in understanding the American story, focusing on these aspects can send the message that history is driven by individuals, rather than institutions that while certainly constructed by individuals, operate as forms of distributed intelligence. An equally valid lens through which one can (and should) understand American history is as a march of of science and technology that shape the lives of individuals via markets. Focusing on a period of American history that is approachable and relavent illustrates this utility of this perspective. This book synthesizes Professor Gordon’s research throughout much of his career, starting from his time in graduate school and the thoroughness sings off of the pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the book argues the following: The period between 1870–1970 was the golden age of American growth and featured an unprecedented improvement in the standard of living for the vast majority of Americans. While the 21st century will certainly contain its fair share of “general purpose” technologies that will be transformative in their own ways, the growth and accompanied improvements in the standard of living will not match those of the previous century. To claim that the following century will be as revolutionary as the previous, one must argue that new technologies (i.e. AI, renewable energy, self driving cars, quantum computing, etc.) will be as important in the every day lives of Americans as was the advent of running water, refrigeration, and electricity. Indeed this is a highly nontrivial argumentative burden. Most of the book focuses on explaining the effect of growth on everyday life. This includes changes in diet, work life, entertainment, communication, transportation, and health. I enjoy this approach to American history because it puts me in the shoes of individuals and offers a much more vivid understanding of the relavent time period than political and military history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing particularly special about these years. Rather, the trends that Gordon describes are continuous, mostly indifferent to political/cultural events, and 
The claim that 1870–1970 was the golden age of growth is a relatively straightforward proposition, but has certain complications. Namely, the U.S. government only started recording GDP in the 1930’s and the metric was changed many times in the following decades to better reflect total productivity in the economy. TODO: Include a brief discussion of some of the interesting sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I claim that GDP has become much less tied to the standard of living than it was in the early 1900s and that improvements in standard of living in the developed world will be almost entirely decoupled from GDP growth in the 21st century, but that is a more subtle argument for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For argument’s sake, I will grant his premise that GDP gr&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;GDP $\neq$ Standard of Living&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A central premise of the book undermines its thesis. In particular, GDP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-takeaways&quot;&gt;Main Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is hard to overstate the magnitude of the anomalous growth in the 1870-1970 period. Based on estimates by Angus Maddison,
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The annual rate of growth in the Western world from AD 1 to AD 1820 was a mere 0.06 percent per year, or 6 percent per century” (Gordon 3).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that does not blow your mind, then you did not read that correctly. It would take about 1000 years for annual production to double, which means that an individual living in almost any time in human history (a time period encompassing ~98% of the human age) could reasonably expect her standard of living to be approximately equal to that of her (great great great) grandparents and her (great great great) grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even if this is true, I do not find it to matter so much. Gordon’s argument has come a long way since this working paper in 2012 which featured this hilarious “social science”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most of the headwinds that Professor Gordon identifies are indeed substantial.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This may be the most important takeaway.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moreover, there is no obvious answer. Indeed, in his review of this book, Paul Krugman answers Gordon’s question with a “definite maybe,” which I claim is the only intelligent answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When starting a chapter, I recommend going straight to the tables/graphs in the chapter and spending a few minutes reading the relavent figures and sources. I enjoyed figured out the major patterns and guessing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found some aspects of the book to be unnecessarily quantitative. An concept such as “standard of living” is inherintly subjective and while I sympathizes with the attempted rigor, the book would have been better off if it relegated GDP per capita, and especially TFP, to a lesser role. Why reduce a concept as interesting and multifacted as standard of living to 2-3 numbers? I could make the critique that TFP is a rather atheoretical and ill-defined but my main issue with it is that even at its best, TFP depends on so many parameters,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, if Gordon wants to “adjust” these measures to include nonmarket factors, then he has to give th&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Gordon</name></author><category term="bookreview" /><summary type="html">Most high school U.S. history courses focus on what I consider to be the dullest aspects of the subject. While an understanding of major political forces, wars, and social movements is invaluable in understanding the American story, focusing on these aspects can send the message that history is driven by individuals, rather than institutions that while certainly constructed by individuals, operate as forms of distributed intelligence. An equally valid lens through which one can (and should) understand American history is as a march of of science and technology that shape the lives of individuals via markets. Focusing on a period of American history that is approachable and relavent illustrates this utility of this perspective. This book synthesizes Professor Gordon’s research throughout much of his career, starting from his time in graduate school and the thoroughness sings off of the pages.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gazing into the Abyss</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/12/21/browning-ordinary-men.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gazing into the Abyss" /><published>2018-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/12/21/browning-ordinary-men</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/12/21/browning-ordinary-men.html">&lt;p&gt;I first heard of this book, strangely enough, through an online lecture by Jordan Peterson. During the summer of 2018, I was asking myself questions about the role of political leaders and the extent to which they do/should reflect the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The idea that leaders ought to reflect the desires of their constituents is almost axiomatic to most Americans. To what extent does this idea remain valid if a leader disagrees with his/her constituents? To what extent should leaders shape the psyche of the nation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting aside the main architects of atrocities, how does a large subset of the population bring itself to carry out the orders of madmen? It seems that there would need to be problems worth identifying at every level of society.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can we prevent such devolution at the levels of individuals, communities, nations, and global community?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe civilizations fall when an uncomfortably large number of individuals becomes agents of its destruction. It seems plausible that guarding against the worst tendencies of humanity will always be a duty of the citizenry. Those tendencies certainly include hatred, envy, and jealosy, but they also include an excessive desire to impress others, a false sense of honor or pride, and an unquestioned submission to authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, this book is not an attempt to psychoanalyze one of maybe 100-1000 commited idealogues with influence. That is the job of many college seniors who decide to read &lt;em&gt;Mein Kampf&lt;/em&gt; while high. Rather, &lt;em&gt;Ordinary Men&lt;/em&gt; tries to shed light on why millions others enabled the vision of a minority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ordinary Men&lt;/em&gt; follows a single battalion of about 500 men during the occupation of Poland. They were part of the Order Police, which is separate from the main army. They were tasked, among other things, with making parts of Poland &lt;em&gt;judenfrei&lt;/em&gt;. In total, these men killed at least 83,000 jews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the the book uses the testimonies of about 125 men during interrogations conducted in the 1960’s. Care must be taken when reading these because memories fade, people suppress certain thoughts, and soldiers may care to exculpate themselves and comrades. Browning also uses soldiers’ personal correspondances sent during the war, along with ample Nazi government records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My takeaway of the book is as follows: Idealogical exremism tautologically represents a small fringe and winning over hearts and minds by the tens of millions is immensely difficult. Those who wish  included 
One minor critique of the book is that there are so many names and ranks to keep track of that many individuals blur together. New soldiers are introduced even at the end of the book. This is complicated by the fact that some people enter and leave the battalion. I recommend keeping track of the consequential people in a notebook and not getting bogged down in the minutia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book mostly tracks the progression from the formation of the battalion,&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christopher Browning</name></author><category term="bookreview" /><summary type="html">I first heard of this book, strangely enough, through an online lecture by Jordan Peterson. During the summer of 2018, I was asking myself questions about the role of political leaders and the extent to which they do/should reflect the population. The idea that leaders ought to reflect the desires of their constituents is almost axiomatic to most Americans. To what extent does this idea remain valid if a leader disagrees with his/her constituents? To what extent should leaders shape the psyche of the nation? Setting aside the main architects of atrocities, how does a large subset of the population bring itself to carry out the orders of madmen? It seems that there would need to be problems worth identifying at every level of society. How can we prevent such devolution at the levels of individuals, communities, nations, and global community?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mathematics for Everyday Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/08/20/ellenberg-math.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mathematics for Everyday Life" /><published>2018-08-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/08/20/ellenberg-math</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bookreview/2018/08/20/ellenberg-math.html">&lt;p&gt;Why should I study math? When will I ever use it? What lessons can the work of mathematicians across the  millenia have for every person in the 21st century? These are the questions that Professor Ellenberg tackles in his phenomenal book. I asked the first two questions rather frequently as a child. I even asked those during my undergraduate and graduate studies! It is natural to ask such questions given that much of modern mathematics seemingly bears little on the natural world. A valid critique of the “unreasonable effectiveness” of mathematics mimics that of “Higher Order Truths About Chmess” by Daniel Dennett. Here are some answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract problems are excellent cross training. Solving such problems sharpens one’s thinking and prepares the mathematical community for more applied problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some problems are much easier to solve at a higher level of analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rather than solve individual problems, it is much more efficent to solve a &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt; of problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solving hard problems, regardless of immediate utility, is fun! There are few feelings that can match that of an epiphany after hours, days, or even years of struggle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mathematician, certain parts of this book seemed obvious when I first read them. For example, of course most important phenomena do not depend linearly on their determinants. Simple regression analyses have important limitations. It needs very little justification that “mathematical expectation” does not refer to the result that one should expect to occur in an average case. These truisms became apparent to me through courses in econometrics, probability, and common sense. However, it is always useful to remember that none of these statements are actually trivial. Their justifications each took a tremendous amount of effort by mathematicians (and those in related fields) to understand deeply. This book tells many of those stories. The intelligencia of yestyear was wrong about many things. But the nature of their errors are educational and sometimes teach more than refined arguments and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During many of my mathematics classes in high school, undergraduate school, and even graduate school, I solved problems and nurtured ways of thinking as if the ideas existed in some alternate reality analagous to Paul Erdos’ conceptualization of “God’s book.” Understanding the stories of these ideas helps to humanize them and contextualize them in everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Criticism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second minor critique proceeds as follows. The book seems poorly titled. A better subtitle may be something of the sort &lt;em&gt;The Power of &lt;strong&gt;Statistical&lt;/strong&gt; Thinking&lt;/em&gt; given that most of the book focuses on lessons of probability and statistics. Professor Ellenberg addresses this by noting that statistics grew out of mathematics and that ideas of probability manifest themselves in many branches of math. Nonetheles,&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jordan Ellenberg</name></author><category term="bookreview" /><summary type="html">Why should I study math? When will I ever use it? What lessons can the work of mathematicians across the millenia have for every person in the 21st century? These are the questions that Professor Ellenberg tackles in his phenomenal book. I asked the first two questions rather frequently as a child. I even asked those during my undergraduate and graduate studies! It is natural to ask such questions given that much of modern mathematics seemingly bears little on the natural world. A valid critique of the “unreasonable effectiveness” of mathematics mimics that of “Higher Order Truths About Chmess” by Daniel Dennett. Here are some answers.</summary></entry></feed>